## Shruti Mehta

Business Data Savvy | Problem Solver | Actively seeking full-time opportunities in Data Analytics and BI

mehta.shru@husky.neu.edu

## Summary

★Turning dull, unsystematic data into meaningful works of art★

A data interpreter, business analyst and information manager with a proven history of turning large data sets into progressive ideas through the creation of summarized analysis, clear, compelling infographics, maps, data visualizations, interactive media and product designs

I am an enthusiastic Information Systems graduate student possessing a humungous potential to learn advanced technologies and adapt to a new environment. I have experience of working with the IT industry giant, Infosys Ltd. for two years. As a Data Analyst, I have worked for one of the potential U.S.' retailers to analyze customer patterns and demonstrate high revenue generating zones.

Additionally, I worked with the Risk and Compliance department of the leading European bank primarily utilizing Regression model to detect fraudulent transactions. With expert skills, I designed schema for database modeling in SQL Server; trained a team of 20 and supported in the creation of queries and reports.

I am very keen on obtaining a Business Data Analyst Role, offering analytical and critical thinking skills to help generate innovative ideas and gain industry experience.

I am self-motivated to learn and explore the world and believe in achieving the goals with the right attitude, hard work, and determination.

#### **★**Skills**★**

Visualization Tools - Tableau, Power BI, TIBCO Spotfire, QlikSense, QlikView, Grafana, Looker Databases / ETL - MySQL, SQL Server, Oracle, SQLite, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, OpenTSDB, SSMS, Alteryx, Spark

Languages - SQL, Python (pandas, numpy, seaborn), R, Java
Analytical Techniques - Regression, Clustering, PCA, Classification, Forecasting
Other tools -MS Azure, MS Visio, UML, Axure, TOAD, SAS, Excel, PowerPoint, AWS, SSRS, Google
Analytics

### Qualities(Clifton Strengths Finder):

Expressive Conversationalist | Flexible Accommodator | Vivid Imaginer | Insightful Noticer | Introspective Thinker

## Experience

## Graduate Teaching Assistant at Northeastern University College of Engineering January 2018 - Present

- Teaching assistant for Big Data Systems and Intelligence Analytics [70 students]
   Responsibilities:
  - √#Help students with the implementation of Machine Learning Algorithms using Python code
  - √#Conduct weekly code walkthroughs
  - ✓#Coordinate with teams over Piazza
  - √#Hold office hours for helping students

## Service Desk Analyst, Information Technology Services (Part Time) at Northeastern University January 2017 - Present

- ✓#Responsible for providing technology infrastructure( laptops, VGA adapters, ethernet cables, laptop chargers), services and applications and services to more than 30,000 students, faculty, alumni and staff at Northeastern University
- ✓#Provide on-call support for the issues with the installation of the software and account management
- √#Escalate major technical issues to the higher management through Service Now by raising tickets
- ✓#Responsible for loaning out laptops, chargers, projectors, tripod stands, and camcorders and maintaining IT infrastructure on campus

## Graduate Teaching Assistant at Northeastern University College of Engineering September 2017 - December 2017 (4 months)

- Teaching Assistant for the course Data Management and Database design [200 students]
   Responsibilities:
  - ✓# Responsible for conducting the lab sessions for students
  - √# Evaluation and grading of the assignments
  - ✓# Reviewing codes
  - ✓# Conducting course-related doubts clearing sessions

# Speaker- Atoms, Axons and Asteroids: Big Data in STEM at Brown University October 2017 - October 2017 (1 month)

 Invited to present and deliver a talk on my research poster "Classification of potentially hazardous asteroid using Deep Neural Network and Calculation of its impact" Code is available at:

https://github.com/MehtaShruti/Asteroids

### Data Analyst Intern at Limelight Networks May 2017 - September 2017 (5 months)

- Operations Analytics
- √#Spearheaded requirement analysis in agile environment; provided techno-functional project management support using JIRA
- √# Extracted and parsed through large volume raw-real-time logs of Splunk's API to identify high
  peaks in network
- ✓# Enhanced customer experience by analyzing factors impacting re-buffering of videos thereby increasing customers' view by 20% Investigated patterns using server KPI and built predictive model to identify recovery time of cloud server
- √# Developed 4 self-serviced ad-hoc Tableau dashboards to forecast network traffic and published reports to server
- √# Collaborated and consulted with Tableau team and successfully deployed Tableau Server on the enterprise-wide server

#### Member

October 2016 - April 2017 (7 months)

The Higher Education Data Warehousing Forum is a network of higher education colleagues dedicated to promoting the sharing of knowledge and best practices regarding knowledge management in colleges and universities, including building data warehouses, developing institutional reporting strategies, and providing decision support.

## Data Analyst at Infosys

July 2014 - June 2016 (2 years)

- Transactions Filtering: Fraud Analytics
- ✓#Performed feature engineering and utilized Logistic Regression using Python to predict transactions as authentic or fraudulent; Further investigated authenticity of fraudulent transactions using Confusion Matrix
- √#Assessed and mitigated risk of fraudulent transactions by generating alerts using optimized SQL and python scripts
- ✓#Automated tabular report generation process of multiple application health check procedures in Excel reducing turnaround

time and cost by 30%

√#Trained 8 peers to carry out daily transactions filtering and monitoring tasks independently.

- √# Awarded "Star of the Month" for exacting business requirements and performing detailed analysis before deadlines
- CRM: Retail, CPG and Logistics
- √# Analyzed customer trend by utilizing unsupervised learning using K-means Clustering over 5 million data points with 120 features
- √# Discovered high revenue generating zones in Europe and created visualization dashboards for more than a dozen online reports

helping clients identify opportunities to sell more advertising

√# Web Scraped to identify current product trends and improve marketing strategies leading to
34% growth in customer acquisition

#### Vice President of Education at Toastmasters International

December 2015 - May 2016 (6 months)

- √#Appointed as the second ranking club officer and was responsible for planning, organising and directing the club program which met the educational needs of the individual members
- √#Chaired the education committee and offered support to the Toastmaster of the meeting to confirm members' role assignments and plan for substitutions if necessary

#### Secretary at Toastmasters International

August 2015 - December 2015 (5 months)

- √#Maintained all club records, managed the club's file, handled club's correspondence and took
  the minutes at each club and executive committee meeting
- ✓#Updated and distributed a roster of the current paid membership and kept the club officers list up-to date for Toastmasters International

## Recruitment and Internships Co-ordinator at University of Petroleum and Energy Studies August 2012 - November 2013 (1 year 4 months)

Regular follow ups with the multinational giants and domain based companies for leveraging the on campus recruitments and internships to the college students.

#### Intern at Oil and Natural Gas Corporation Ltd

June 2013 - July 2013 (2 months)

Developed an Online Internship Registration Portal for the organization and implemented a 3-tier architecture using ASP.NET, C# and ADO.NET

### Intern at Mawana Sugars Ltd

June 2011 - July 2011 (2 months)

I, with a team of four members got involved with the technical experts in implementing a Bus Network Topology in the organisation. I learned about the Networks Architectures and Server implementation in their Data Center

## Education

Northeastern University

Master's Degree, Management Information Systems, 2016 - 2018

Activities and Societies: Global Leadership Institute(Lead 360)

University of Petroleum and Energy Studies

Bachelor's Degree, Bachelor of Technology(B.Tech), Computer Science Engineering, 2010 - 2014 Activities and Societies: Computer Society of India, AIEEE, Society of Petroleum Engineers, Placements Team, Cultural Team, Anchoring Team, Sports Team, actively participated in co-curricular and extra curricular activities, organized numerous events and workshops, served as a member in Computer Society of India, Internal Public Relations Coordinator in Society of Petroleum Engineers and Placements Cell of the college.

### Honors and Awards

Competent Communicator, Competent Leader, Advanced Leader Bronze, Scholar

## Shruti Mehta

Business Data Savvy | Problem Solver | Actively seeking full-time opportunities in Data Analytics and BI

mehta.shru@husky.neu.edu



Contact Shruti on LinkedIn